Now I have decided to take a health insurance
policy.  But the next question is
how much should the health insurance policy cost?  10 lakh, 20 lakh, 50 lakh
or 1 crore?  This question comes to everyone's mind.
So I will answer this question today through this video.  We will
talk in detail about
how much should actually be taken and why
should it be taken and what is the session?  And finally we will
also talk about premiums.  So stay tuned
till the end of the video.  This is going to be a very useful
video.
[Music] Let's go to the
video.  If
you take health insurance, how much should you take?  10 lakh, 20 lakh, 50
lakh or here I would like to say that if
we talk even 10 years ago, the
treatment cost of many things was very
low.  Today the treatment cost is very high.
Going to the hospital means it costs ₹00 lakh
a day.  Meaning, I am sure
many people must have experienced
that it easily costs ₹00 to lakhs a day.
You just enter and you are coming home in two days.
Because
we have seen that on daily basis, we make claims that it is very
rare that a claim is of Rs 300-400.  The
average claim size is Rs 3 lakh to Rs 4 lakh.
If you are hospitalized for three to four days
, some
procedure is being done, some surgery is being done
, then this much claim definitely comes.  Because the
treatment cost is so high.  And if
any critical illness occurs, then there
is no limit on the claim.  Many times it happens
that in critical illness the starting
claim itself is Rs 3 lakh, 4 lakh and it goes up to
crore.  And if the policy there is of Rs 4 lakh, 5 lakh
or 10 lakh then will it be enough in the
future.  The second risk is that now that the
critical illness has been diagnosed, the
insurance company will not provide the policy or will
not enhance it because the
insurance company knows that now these
claims will be recurring and we cannot extend the policy.
So many times people are left in dilemma as to
what to do now?  So let me just
give you some data points.
Talking about cancer treatment, in 2013, the
complete treatment of cancer used to cost ₹13.5 lakh.
After 10 years,
in 2024, after 11 years, it costs a minimum of ₹50 lakh
for a cancer treatment to cure the cancer.
Now it depends on what stage it is,
what type of cancer it is, whether it is multiple cancers,
what is the stage?  So it depends on all those things.
But the minimum side pay average
claim size is ₹50 lakh.  Heart
transplant used to cost ₹9.8 lakh in 2013.  Worth
approximately Rs 10 lakh.  As of today, it has increased more
than three times.
Heart transplant surgery costs 34 lacs.
Now it's just a surgery.  Let us assume that there are recurring
expenses before and after this.
Some other organ may get
affected.
We are not even talking about the later expenses.  We are
talking only about the main treatment.   There
is liver cirrhosis.  A transplant was needed.  The
cost was ₹7 lakh in 2013.  Today
in 2024, I am talking about one year ago.  The
data is ₹24 lakh which is almost 3.5
times.  Kidney transplant has become common.
Now you will see that many people are undergoing kidney
transplant surgeries.  Earlier it
was 5 lakhs in 2013.  In 2024 it is 18.2
lakhs.  I just made the claim one
to two months ago.  There was a claim for kidney transplant.  I
think it is between 28 to 30 lakhs.
Which is only the hospitalization bill.
Pre-post hospitalization is different.
So you should understand that on an average, if you suffer from
any critical illness, if we
talk about the future, then the adequate sum
assured is not 5 lakh, 10 lakh and 20 lakh, it
is way higher.  So today we will
talk about what is the solution to it
and what should be done.  So
you cannot change health inflation.  Health inflation of 14-15% is a
normal thing.  This means that
your treatment cost will definitely double in six to seven years.
Here you can see that it has happened
triple or even four times in 10 years.
If the cost is four times.  Cancer
treatment was Rs 13 lakh or is it Rs 51 lakh.   It
cost almost four times more.  I have done some
calculations for you.  Just
to give you an idea that actually when we
say higher cover then the cost will also
increase.  Higher cover is not coming for free.  But there is
a myth that I want to bust
here.  Many times you people say
that you want to take higher cover
but who will pay its premium?  But
today I am going to break this myth that
higher cover does not mean that it comes at a very
high cost.  If you are
taking an average policy of Rs 10 lakh, then it is not that for Rs 20 lakh or Rs 50 lakh the
premium will increase five times or double or if you take Rs 1 crore then it will increase
10 times.  It's not like that.
Its cost is still going to remain controlled.
Because the
company always gives you rebate on higher sum assured.  Currently the average
claim size is low in India.  As
this increases, the premiums for higher sum assured will
increase.  But if you take a higher sum
assured now, your
premiums will be lower.  Let's see how.
I have taken some examples from some companies.
We have taken four companies here.  I have
taken four plans.  Age is 31 litres.
Calculating premium on location Delhi.
You know that the premium is calculated according to your zone.
So I've taken the premium of Zone One.
If you live in Zone 2 or Zone 3, the
premium will be even lower.   There
is a detailed video about zonal premiums and payments to zonal.   Don't
forget to watch that.  Want to understand
why there is actually a difference in the premiums of zones?  So its link
is in the description box.  So
if I am taking policy of Age 31 location Delhi 10 lakh then
Niva Reshore 2.0 Titanium Plus,
no rider is taken here.
There is no optional cover.  Only the basic
features are included.  And these
premiums are inclusive of 18% GST.
So the premium is ₹1,880
₹1,880 for one year.  If we
take a policy of Rs 20 lakh, then the premium will be Rs 18,000.  If
we take a policy of Rs 50 lakh, then the
premium will be Rs 23,000.  This means that for double premium
you are getting five times extra cover.  The
premium for 10 lakhs was Rs 12,000, the premium for 50 lakhs
is Rs 23,000, you are paying double the premium.  You are
giving 12,000 more.  But how much cover are you getting
?  50 lakhs.  Rest of the no claim
bonuses are different for every policy and their benefits
are separate.  Right now we are talking only about base sum
assured.  Then comes
HDFC Ergo Optima Secure Pay,
your premium is Rs 17,000 for 10 lakhs.
₹1,000 for Lax Just ₹2000 extra your
cover is doubled.  And then
almost similar cost for 15 LE is ₹3,000
premium only.  ICIC LBA Elevate 10 Lac
for One Year is Rs.9500.  The premium for 20 lakhs is
₹1,943, the
premium for 50 lakhs is ₹16,633,
so your premium has not even doubled
for 50 lakhs.  Where
you are getting 50 lakhs cover for Rs 9500 and Rs 165000.
Aditya Birla Active One Max comes with
₹100 for 10 lax covers, ₹1000 for 20
lax covers and ₹1000 for ₹10 lax covers.
Here it is 1.7 times and you get five times the
cover.  So we live under the myth
that the premium will increase.  Don't take too much cover.
Let's go for lower sum assured.   Is it any
less than this?  Many people also
ask this.  But will you do it for less than this
?  If the treatment is not completed,
you will have to withdraw money from your savings.
Your remaining financial planning will have to be spoiled.
Then what is the point of
buying insurance?  So 10 lakh, 20 lakh, 50
lakh, now you can decide yourself
how much cover you should take.  I have
not taken Rs 1 crore here yet.  Even if you take Rs 1 crore, it is
not like that, the premium will increase 10 times.
7 By increasing the amount by 8000, 10,000 and you will get
insurance up to Rs 1 crore.  So it is
better to buy 1 crore.  Now many
times it happens that one is not able to afford the
premium.  Okay, we can give only Rs 10 lakh.
What should one do on top of that?   They
also want their sum assured to be higher.
Like a situation like Covid had happened.  We all
want more insurance but do
n't want to pay the premium.  So for that there
is a cheap solution which is called Super Topup.
So I have made detailed videos.  You
should buy base, base plus super top up
, what are the benefits, what are the disadvantages,
you can prefer all that there.  Here
I will talk about Mayor Premiums.  So
if you just want a backup that
suppose tomorrow some expense exceeds Rs 10 lakh,
it will be covered by my super topup
and I will have to pay less premium.  So that
is also session.  So as you can see in front of you,
I have also withdrawn the super topup premiums of the same companies.
For example,
in Nima Bupa, 90 lakh with 10 lakh deductible, 10, so
you took the base and paid ₹12,000
premium here.  If you pay ₹1000
more along with Super Topup, you will get insurance of ₹90 lakh.
Now this will not be full comprehensive coverage.
Some things will not be covered.  There will be
limits on some things.
But at least something is better than
nothing.  It is better to take a policy of just Rs 10 lakh.
You can take 10 + 90.  If you are
not going to take higher base sum assured
due to any reason, if you are still
not convinced that you do not want higher sum assured then
go for super top up. HDFC R also has
super top up which is of ₹20 lakh with 5 lakh
deductible whose premium is ₹2500
for insurance of only 20 lakh which will
work for your sum assured of 10 lakh. In ICICI LBAD,
super top up of ₹10 lakh is available for ₹2000.
Super top-up of ₹2800 is available at Aditya Birla.
So basically
if you have taken the base plan of ₹1,
you can also take a super top up on it to enhance your
coverage.  Even if you have taken a base cover of Rs 50,
still take this super top-up as a
backup, that is, take it with Rs 10 because
that is not your sum assured amount.
But even if you take 50 and one CR,
still add super topup because you
never know when and how much you will need and when you
actually need it, you will not be
able to take it.  So by taking a low sum assured, you are
playing with your own security, that is, with the security of your family.   I am
not justifying it.  I am
harsh here but I know the reality.  In what manner do
people take insurance policies and
what is their reaction when claims come,
then they say please ma'am please
increase it somehow, you can increase it by doing anything, it is
not possible and
we see claims day in and day out, so
now when there is time, it is a good time, we have
time, then why not buy the cover right now without
thinking twice, first preference
is to go for a higher base cover, so that there is a big
policy in which there is comprehensive coverage,
all modern treatments, robotic surgery,
everything is covered, there are no restrictions,
non payable items are covered.  If
you do not want to take that then at least
take a super top up with a policy of Rs 10 lakh.  And even
if you take a big policy, still take a super top
up.  What goes away?  The insurance company is providing a cover of ₹00 ₹3000 per year.
Enjoy the low premium as long as it is there.  Get higher cover.
So my answer to this question is 10 lakh,
20 lakh, 50 lakh definitely 50 lakhs and
1 crore not less than that.  Go for higher cover
because this is not a choice.  This is now a compulsion.
We have no option now.  So that's what
I just wanted to highlight.  So that
you take the right decision for your family.
Because you are their provider.  If
you take a wrong decision tomorrow, your family may
tell you that you could not even take this much care.  So,
take the right decision in the right way.  If you want to connect
with our team for any guidance, please do so.
Contact number, email ID is given below.
You can also fill out a Google form.  Our
team will connect you.
Quick reminder before we go, if you have
n't subscribed to our channel yet, do so.
So that you get the right infection at the right
time.  See you in the next video.  Till then
stay safe, take care, bye.